CHAPTER 1

Introduction

Maritime historians of the early modern age have produced works that deal with European presence, commercial expansion, goods and commodities traded, interaction with people, migration and scientific encounters around the world. Tapan Raychaudhuri, R.N. Banerjee and S. Arasaratnam were the pioneers to focus on the Coromandel Coast and they dealt chiefly with merchants, trading practices, organizational and institutional aspects of the Dutch and the English East India Companies and the overall structure of overseas commerce.1 Following them a group of historians culled statistical data from European records to know the concrete realities on economic and social history of the Coromandel (including Tamil and Telugu country) and their seminal studies, linked the local developments with commercial exchange that took place at the global level.2 Yet there are many new and unexplored avenues on the European impact of maritime trade and so this book aims to explore the slave trade and human migration from the Tamil coast to ports around the world.

S. Arasaratnam and Markus Vink outlined the subject of slave trade that was carried out in the Bay of Bengal and Indian Ocean.3 Sanjay Subrahmanyam, while covering the region of South India never touched on the slave trade of the Europeans.4 In fact no reliable study that dwells upon Tamil society and the impact of slave trading developed through various new trading routes connecting the new slave markets that emerged in the age of colonial slavery is available. There is a pressing need to have this regional study in order to examine and compare the slave trade of the Europeans in the Atlantic which affected largely the African and American society in the early modern period at the global level. Colonialism was a global phenomenon that not only defined the territories subjected to its rationale and destructive rule, but also shaped European history in profound yet still reluctantly recognized ways. A majority of the works deal emphatically with British colonialism. They do not discuss aspects of other European overseas empires. A more pluralistic approach to the question of colonialism and postcolonial legacy must begin with identifying the parameters of the various participating empires.

The book seeks to explain how Europeans sought to understand slavery prevalent in Tamil country. Thereafter they developed trading strategies and operations in slave trade. Each of the East India Companies dealt with slaves and slave trade separately but their volume and value of business had differed owing to various reasons. The sprawling slave trade networks through intercontinental trade led to personal interest and corporate policy enabling the circulation of slaves around the world. The East India trading companies fashioned their own system and practices, with a conscious blend of collaboration with local agents, brokers and merchants in slave trade.

Slavery in Medieval Tamil country was a mode of labour. It is to be mentioned that overseas transportation of slaves never happened prior to the coming of the Europeans. How slaves were exported overseas and this change occurred needs to be examined. One could ask broader questions, such as whether there are any shadow sides and links between slave trade of the East India Companies and colonialism. Did large scale exploitation develop through the slave trade and had slavery and labour been linked and combined together? How did slavery and slave trade cause further damage towards descendants of slaves and their next generation? What types of crimes were committed against humanity by the European trading companies? Thus, the stories of slavery and slave trade remain untold till date and should be traced.

SOURCES AND METHODS

Transnational methods are most suitable for writing maritime history to understand the process of globalization that dates back to the sixteenth century. European empires began to expand overseas and the inter-imperial connections and cross-cultural interactions are important for the progression of colonial expansion. By studying the flows of people, commodities and ideas which crossed national boundaries in this period, historians could offer new insights in the operation of colonialism.

The study culls information from Portuguese and Spanish records on the slave trade. It also uses Dutch, Danish, French and English East India Company documents and German missionary reports. The work focuses on the basic questions of how and why the slave trade was generated and sustained by these European companies from the Tamil coast. It evaluates explicitly and makes it known whether the slave traffic arose from the demand side or the supply side. It argues that the European capitalism developed since the mid-sixteenth century, had created necessary conditions that turned a human being into a commodity for sale. It led to produce a colonial proletariat in the form of manual labour undertaken both by the European privateers and the East India Companies. As a result slaves came to be widely transported and transplanted from many European trading enclaves on the Tamil coast to various destinations in Asia, Africa and America.

THE BOOK’S STRUCTURE

Chapter 1 introduces the theme, maritime history of the Tamil Coast from a historiographical perspective. Chapter 2 traces the presence of slaves in Tamil society and situates the sale of slaves engraved on stones and employed by medieval temples and madams. Slavery had continued as one notices the slave sale deeds on palm leaves. The chapter thus deals with the theme particularly of Tamil society and slaves in transition from medieval to pre-colonial rule.

Chapter 3 outlines the Portuguese slave trade developed from the Tamil Coast to Goa and Cochin in India, with ports of Melaka and Aceh in South East Asia during 1547 and 1625. It discusses how the Kings of Portugal in Lisbon and the Viceroys in Goa issued regulations on slavery and slave trade from time to time. Portuguese private merchants purchased slaves from Tamil Coast. The study traces the accounts of a Tamil slave in Goa in 1548 and escape of a Tamil slave in Cochin from his master in 1558. The Jesuit missionaries on the Tamil Coast wrote at length on slavery and slave trade in their letters sent to Europe during 1545-1552. The discussion on slavery and slaves took place at the Provincial Council held in Goa in 1567 and it framed rules from the ecclesiastical point of view. However, private Portuguese slave trade thrived from Nagapattinam to Melaka from 1616 to 1625. Portuguese slave trade had also extended from Nagapattinam to Aceh in Sumatra in 1621.

Chapter 4 evaluates the slave exports from the Tamil Coast to the foreign long-distance markets through the Portuguese slave trade conducted with Spanish Manila and further growth of Spanish slave trade with Mexico during 1616 and 1704. Private Portuguese trade in slaves flourished from Nagapattinam to Manila between 1616 and 1689. One finds numerous sale and resale of Tamil slaves in Manila of various castes including paraiyars, vellalars, valaiyars, reddis and Tamil Muslims. These slaves in Manila were largely employed in the coconut palm cultivation works in 1646. The Spaniards transported the Tamil slaves purchased again in Manila and exported them to colonial Mexico. These slaves who crossed the Pacific were employed in the coconut palm tree plantations in Mexico in 1619. Some Tamil slaves in Mexico were also employed in textile workshops. One finds a slave of the udaiyar caste in Manila sold and transported and again resold in Mexico in 1643.

Chapter 5 enumerates the export of slaves from Pazhaverkadu to Jakarta by the Dutch Company during 1621-65. An exercise is made to cull statistics from the Dutch records. 2,911 slaves were purchased in 1621-4 in Pazhaverkadu and exported to Jakarta. 880 slaves were transported in 1625 in ships to Jakarta. 1,082 slaves were transported during 1627-31. Slave purchases dwindled when slaves were not available. Therefore one finds 87 slaves exported during 1634-7 and 265 slaves were purchased during 1640-5 and exported to Jakarta. However, later the Dutch purchases swelled and increased and the company purchased 2,117 slaves in 1646 and 1,915 slaves in 1647. The export and supply decreased to 56 between 1648 and 1651 because slaves were not available. 1,059 slaves were exported to Jakarta during 1660-5. One also finds the export of 98 persons captured during naval sieges against Portuguese being declared as slaves from Pazhaverkadu to Jakarta between 1630 and 1643. The death of 1,086 slaves occurred during the slave voyages from Pazhaverkadu to Jakarta during 1622-48.

Chapter 6 examines the Dutch slave trade and shipping slaves from Pazhaverkadu to Syriam in Myanmar between 1638 and 1679. The study also traces the rules framed for slave trade by the Dutch East India Company. The chapter also analyses slave exports from Devanampattinam and Porto Novo to Jakarta, Aceh and Banten under the Dutch Company during 1624-88. According to statistics culled from records, 1,683 slaves were exported during 1624-30 in Dutch ships from Devanampattinam to Jakarta. 461 slaves purchased in Kunimedu during 1624-7 were exported from Devanampattinam to Jakarta. 197 slaves were sent in 1635-6 from Devanampattinam to Jakarta. 27 slaves were exported in 1651. 166 slaves were transported in 1660-2 from Devanampattinam to Jakarta. 133 slaves were exported in 1644 in Dutch ships from Tirumullaivasal to Jakarta. 729 slaves were again purchased and exported in 1646 from Tirumullaivasal. 1,976 slaves were purchased and exported from Karaikal to Jakarta during 1646-7. 31 slaves were again purchased and exported from Karaikal in 1651. The voluminous slave trade led to the resistance of the local ruler banning slave trade of the Dutch Company in 1688.

Chapter 7 discusses Dutch slave trade operated from Nagapattinam to Colombo, Banten, Jakarta, Melaka and the social realities of the enslaved between 1655 and 1704. It is found that 4,195 slaves were purchased and exported during 1655 and 1656 in Dutch ships from Nagapattinam to Colombo. 6,793 Tamil slaves were purchased and exported between 1659 and 1661 in ships from Nagapattinam to Colombo. 46 slaves were purchased in 1660 and exported to Banten. 1,202 slaves were purchased in 1660 and exported to Jakarta. 213 slaves were purchased in 1660 and exported to Melaka. 5 slaves were purchased in 1663 and sent in Dutch ships from Sadurangapattinam to Melaka. The Dutch company transported 703 Portuguese soldiers and residents as war prisoners declared as slaves from Nagapattinam to Jakarta in 1658. One finds re-distribution of Nagapattinam slaves by the Dutch Company from Colombo to Jakarta during 1678-83. The study also dwells on the continued slave purchases and trade at Nagapattinam under the Dutch during 1694 and 1704.

The chapter also explores the Dutch slave trade conducted from Nagapattinam to Cape Town and Colombo during 1705 and 1791. Slave purchases and exports continued from Nagapattinam to Africa in 1705-39 and also in 1763-75. One finds purchase and sale of many slaves on the Coromandel Coast by the naval officers of the Dutch Company during 1737 and 1743. The study dwells on the growth of slave exports from Nagapattinam to Sri Lanka during 1766-91.

Chapter 8 elaborates slave trade and traffic in Tuticorin developed under the Dutch company from 1660 to 1791. Transportation of slaves began from Tuticorin to Cape Town in South Africa and to the Netherlands on a large scale during 1694-1734. The slave trade of the Dutch Company continued to South Africa and Sri Lanka during 1730-80. One finds manumission of Tuticorin slaves in Colombo between 1739 and 1791. According to statistics 1710 slaves were transported from the port of Tuticorin to Sri Lanka between 1755 and 1791. The study covers domestic slavery prevalent in Tuticorin and the pathetic lives of the slaves too. The chapter also outlines an interesting case study of a slave from Tuticorin and the circuits of his journey to the Netherlands, Germany and British North America during 1739-63. Madhan, a Tamil slave abducted from his father was sold to an employee of the Dutch Company in Tuticorin in 1739. He travelled along with his master to the Netherlands in 1741. His master took him to Germany where he was converted and received baptism with the new name, Samuel Johannes in 1746. Even after becoming a Christian, he remained a slave. He was sent to the seminary at Barbay for his education and he stayed there from 1746 to 1753. He was sent to Herrnhut and he ran away in March 1754. The surrender and arrest of Samuel Johannes at Barby had been reported in May 1754. Thereafter Samuel Johannes was transported to Pennsylvania in British North America. He lived there since 1754 and got married to an African slave. Finally he died in 1763. This chapter underlines the living experience of the Tamil slave.

Chapter 9 explores the English East India Company export of slaves from Madras to St Helena colony in South Atlantic between 1654 and 1712 for development of sugar plantations. It also traces the English Company slave trade from Madras to Bengkulu on the West Coast of Sumatra between 1682 and 1748 where the transported slaves had been employed in the shipyard.

Chapter 10 focuses on slavery, slave trade and the seascapes of Tranquebar under the Danes between 1632 and 1790. It outlines the beginning of the Danish slave trade in 1632 and the subsequent growth of the private traders shipping slaves to the port of Kedah in Malaysia and Aceh in Sumatra during 1646-7. The Lutheran missionaries who noticed the system of slavery in Tranquebar communicated the details to Europe. They described the local slavery and made comparison with slavery prevalent in Germany. The Lutheran missionaries also explained the various methods of slave traps adopted by the native slave dealers in Tranquebar. Slaves were converted to Christianity in the Danish colony as found in the records of 1707-8. The internal migration facilitated increasing slave exports from Tranquebar to Aceh in Sumatra and Cape Town in South Africa between 1727 and 1749. Pratap Singh the king of Thanjavur reacted sharply to the slave purchases and growth of trade by the Danes between 1741 and 1744. This made the Danish Governor issue an order of prohibition for slave trade in Tranquebar in 1745. As a result after introduction of prohibition illegal slave trade came to be developed by the traders between 1745 and 1753. The Danish governor who sensed the threat and danger from the native ruler, came to introduce the abolition of slave trade and the order was issued in Tranquebar in 1753. Government orders were again issued for ending the slavery in Tranquebar between 1783 and 1790. The study traces Tranquebar born slaves found in Sri Lanka, Cape Town, Mauritius and Denmark between 1775 and 1794.

Chapter 11 illuminates the export of slaves from Pondicherry under the French East India Company. The role of the native brokers and merchants and the rulers is explored in this context. The Nawab of Arcot had his own policy towards French slave trade and so the Company had to adopt several methods for obtaining slaves for overseas export. Shipping and French slave trade during 1707 and 1760 had extended from Pondicherry to Mauritius and Reunion. A statistics of 588 slaves exported during 1729-32 had been furnished. The French Company developed purchase of slaves from Karaikal. One notices sale of 26 male and 23 female slaves and transportation to Mauritius and Le Reunion during 1766-76. Case studies of slaves have been presented: while the first deals with a slave of Pondicherry exported to France in 1750 and the legal battle held during 1759, the second traces how a slave exported from Mauritius to Pondicherry after his stay for many years, made his escape and returned in a ship to Pondicherry in 1785. Interesting insights emerge from the slave register maintained at Pondicherry and one finds the geographical origin of slaves with place names in the hinterland, the selling price in Pondicherry port town held in the slave auction on various dates in 1783.

Chapter 12 deals with the conclusion and reports the findings of the study. The book explains the fluidity of oceans that calls for a global perspective and the transnational perspectives to analyse oceans, seas and waterways. There has been a shift in maritime studies by looking not from hinterland to sea but from ocean to coast in the modern period. This study thus brings for a rigorous incorporation of the littoral Tamil communities into world history. It shows that oceans can change understandings of global networks of connectivity and also geographic concepts of borders and horizons, subverting notions of imperial hierarchies of power. Understanding the oceans as vibrant living spaces this volume provides a way to transcend spatial and temporal categories to dive deeper into oceanic movement of people and colonial history.

NOTES

1. Tapan Raychaudhuri, Jan Company in Coromandel, 1603-1690: A Study in the Interrelations of European Commerce and Traditional Economies, The Hague, 1962; R.N. Banerjee, Economic Progress of the East India Company on the Coromandel Coast, 1702-1746, Nagpur, 1974; Sinnapah Arasaratnam, Merchants, Companies and Commerce on the Coromandel Coast, 1650-1740, Delhi, 1980.

2. Bhaskarjyoti Basu, The Central Coromandel in the Eighteenth Century, Ph.D. Dissertation, Visva-Bharati, 1989; Bhaswathi Bhattacharaya, The Dutch East India Company on the Coromandel Coast, 1740-1780, A Study of its Decline, Ph.D. Dissertation, Visva-Bharati, 1992; Lalitha Iyer, Trade and Finance on the Coromandel Coast, 1757-1853, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Hyderabad, 1993; S. Jeyaseela Stephen, The Coromandel Coast and its Hinterland: Economy, Society and Political System, 1500-1600, Manohar, Delhi, 1997; Kanakalatha Mukund, The Trading World of the Tamil Merchant: Evolution of Merchant Capitalism in the Coromandel, Hyderabad, 1999; Arvind Sinha, The Politics of Trade: Anglo-French Commerce on the Coromandel Coast, 1763-1793, Manohar, Delhi, 2002; P. Swarnalatha, The World of the Weaver in the Northern Coromandel, 1750-1850, Hyderabad, 2005; S. Jeyaseela Stephen, Expanding Portuguese Empire and the Tamil Economy, Sixteenth-Eighteenth Centuries, Delhi, 2009; Radhika Seshan, Trade and Politics on the Coromandel Coast, Seventeenth and Early Eighteenth Centuries, Delhi, 2012; S. Jeyaseela Stephen, Oceanscapes: Tamil Textiles in the Early Modern World, Delhi, 2014.

3. S. Arasaratnam, ‘Slave Trade in the Indian Ocean, in K.S., Mathew, ed., Mariners, Merchants and Oceans, Delhi, 1995, pp. 195-208; Markus Vink, ‘The World’s Oldest Trade: Dutch Slavery and Slave Trade in the Indian Ocean in the Seventeenth Century’, Journal of World History, vol. 14, no. 2, June 2003, pp. 131-46.

4. Sanjay Subrahmanyam, The Political Economy of Commerce, Southern India, 1500-1650, London, 1990.